Guide to the College of Human Ecology Centennial Records, ca. 1991-2001
College of Human Ecology Centennial Records,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York State College of Human Ecology Centennial records [ca.1991-2001].
23-2-3169
1.6 Cubic Feet.
Minutes of meetings, Memoranda, Brochures, Course Background Material, and Time Capsule.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records concerning the year-long College of Human Ecology Centennial Celebration (2000-01) and the related development program.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records concerning the year-long College of Human Ecology Centennial Celebration (2000-01) and the related development program, including minutes of meetings, memoranda, brochures, background on Joan Jacobs Brumberg's course "Archival Research: Exploring the History of Home Economics" and the subsequent exhibition "From Domesticity to Modernity: What Was Home Economics?" Includes a CD of the exhibition web site and a time capsule created by Human Ecology students, to be opened in 2025.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Brumberg, Joan Jacobs.; Cornell University-Students.
Subjects:
Home economics-History.; Human ecology-History.; Home economics-Exhibitions .; Home economics-Study and teaching.; Time capsules.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 2 is restricted - not to be opened until 2025.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Calendar of Events
Box 1 folder 1
Series II. Planning and Development
Box 1 folders 2-16
Series III. Centennial Events
Box 1 folders 17-30
Series IV. Exhibits
Series V. Centennial Exhibit: "From Domesticity to Modernity: What Was Home Economics?" Kroch Library
Box 1 folders 31-49
series VI. HD 455 "Archival Research: Exploring the History of Home Economics" (Joan Jacobs Brumberg)
Box 1 folders 50-55
series VII. History and Background to Centennial Events
Box 1 folders 56-61
series VIII. Time Capsule
Box 2
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Calendar of Events
  - Calendar of Events, May-August 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cornell Academic-Year Calendar featuring the College of Human Ecology
- Series II. Planning and Development
  - Deans and Chairs- meetings and memos, 1998-05-1999-08 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Centennial Task Force, 2000-01 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Working Group memos, 2000-01-2000-07 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Steering Committee: members, meeting minutes, memos, 1999-05-2000-08 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Timeline project: Lynne Byall Benson, 2000-01 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Nomination of Martha Van Rensselaer to National Women's Hall of Fame, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Previous Martha Van nominations to the Hall of Fame, 1981, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York State Encyclopedia entry: "Home Economics" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cornell University academic year calendar featuring Human Ecology: photo locations, correspondence, development, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Development of Centennial logo and slogan, December 1999 - July 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Centennial Celebration buttons, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reproduction of "Saving Steps", by MVR, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stationery, cards, invitations, brochures (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Centennial publicity, 2000-06-2001-08 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Web publicity, 2000-10-2001-04 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series III. Centennial Events
  - Events overview: Barbecue, library grant, satellite video conferences, Cooperative Extension events (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Historians' lunch, 2002-06 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Centennial Weekend: planning and development (schedules, correspondence, invitations, memos), 2000-04-2001-03 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Centennial Weekend: Final plans, March 30-31, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Centennial Weekend: Keynote speaker, Henry W. Foster, Jr., M.D., 2001-03-30-2001-03-31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Proposed Centennial film, (Lucy Jarvis), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York City Gala Event, April 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - CHE 110th-President Hunter Rawling's Speech, 2001; V-5837 (Box 1)
- Series IV. Exhibits
  - Martha Van Rensselaer's life before Cornell: exhibit in Kroch, Reunion, 2000-06 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Centennial displays in MVR Hall lobby and in alumni case, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mann Library web site: "Core Historical Literature of Home Economics", used at Emeritus event, 2000-08 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mann Library exhibit: history of the College of Home Economics, 2000-10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Day Hall display, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Art Exhibits at Kendal and in Kroch: Clara Straight, Virginia True, Dora Erway, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Common Threads"/"Uncommon Threads" exhibits at Johnson Museum of Art (Textiles and Apparel, Charlotte Jirousek), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series V. Centennial Exhibit: "From Domesticity to Modernity: What Was Home Economics?"
  - Text for exhibit, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Centennial Exhibit web site: Faculty biographies, marriage course (Lemo Rockwood), oral biographies (Florence Beck and Doris Mitchell), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Overview case; scanned photos for all cases, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Home sewing case, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Case 1: Was Home Economics a Profession?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Case 2: What Kind of Research Did Home Economists Do?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Case 3: What Careers Did Home Economics Include?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Case 4: What Was the Impact of the College of Home Economics on a National and International Level?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Case 5: What Formats and Techniques Did Home Economists Use to Educate the Public?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Case 6: What Role Did Home Economics Play in the National Emergencies of the 20th Century?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Case 7: How Did Home Economists Influence American Consumer Culture, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Case 8: How Did Home Economics Students See Themselves?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Case 9: What Were Practice Apartments?, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Case 10: What Was the Role of Home Economics in the Life of the University?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Case 11: Why the Change to Human Ecology?, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Suffrage and Eleanor Roosevelt, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Exhibit banners/sails, flyers, invitations, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Timeline - cloth 1 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Series VI. HD 455 "Archival Research: Exploring the History of Home Economics" (Joan Jacobs Brumberg)
  - Course description, syllabus, development of course, 1999-12-2000-10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Students who did Kroch exhibit, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Fall
  - Required reading, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Annotated bibliography done by students in HD 455, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Final exhibit critique, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Evaluation form and completed evaluations, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Series VII. History and Background to Centennial Events
  - Home Economics exhibit: "History of the College of Home Economics" program, outline, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Histories of land-grant colleges, Cornell and the College of Human Ecology (including Martha Van Rensselaer); other articles on home economics and its historical backdrop (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Portraits and photographs (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - CHE Mission and Objectives (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - CD of exhibition web site (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Responses and recognition that the exhibit and web site have received, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Series VIII. Time Capsule
  - Time Capsule compiled by Human Ecology students who were members of VOICES - includes: Photograph album, publications, shirts, scrapbook Restricted - To be opened in 2025, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Posters from various events during the centennial (Box Ms. Box 52)